I remember, once, I heard
Ricordo, una volta, avevo sentito
that the world’s leading authority on Hinduism, so-called,
che la massima autorità del cosiddetto Induismo,
who would like write the encyclopedia entry.
che scriveva le voci nelle enciclopedie.
Now it’s Wikipedia, but in the old days …
Ora c'è Wikipedia, ma ai vecchi tempi...
You can read about it online, [Laughing]
potete leggere queste cose online, [Ride]
people had books and libraries,
le persone avevano i libri, e le librerie,
and these things called encyclopedias.
e queste cose chiamate enciclopedie.
[I am God?]
[Sono Dio?]
And so he would write like that section.
E dunque lui scriveva quella parte.
His name was A.L. Basham, he wrote a book called
Il suo nome era A. L. Basham,
So he was giving a lecture at UCLA,
Dava una conferenza alla UCLA,
University of California, Los Angeles.
University of California, Los Angeles.
I thought I would go meet him, see what he was saying.
Pensavo di incontrarlo, vedere cosa diceva.
I could see what was sweet about him,
Potei vedere la sua dolcezza,
this stodgy old British gentleman—
questo vecchio noioso signore Britannico.
he was really a closet Krishnaite,
Era davvero un Krishnaita nascosto,
in his heart, you could really see, he was a devotee.
nel suo cuore, si poteva chiaramente vedere che era un devoto.
And one of the things I thought he said was very sweet.
E una delle cose che disse pensai fosse molto dolce.
At first he was talking about different gods and goddesses,
Inizialmente stava parlando dei diversi dèi e dèe,
like we’ve heard Mark Twain: Huckleberry Finn, Tom Sawyer.
come abbiamo sentito da Mark Twain —sapete, Huckleberry Finn, Tom Sawyer—
He said, “In religion India is the only millionaire.
disse: «Nella religione, l'India è l'unico milionario.
All the other religions are paupers in comparison,
Tutte le altre religioni sono povere in confronto,
India is the only millionaire.”
India è l'unico milionario».
Meaning, millions of gods and goddesses.
Voleva dire, milioni di dèi e dèe.
So, he gave a slide show and he said,
Mostrò delle diapositive e disse:
“And they’re making more.”
«E ne stanno facendo altri».
Just like we have Kṛṣṇa with the Dasavatars,
Proprio come abbiamo Kṛṣṇa con i Dasavatara,
Kṛṣṇa in the centre and the ten Avatars round,
Kṛṣṇa nel centro e i dieci Avatara intorno,
they showed one Shram Devata, the Goddess of Technology.
mostrarono una certa Shram Devata, la Dea della Tecnologia.
And they showed like in the ten things: a rocket ship, a tractor,
E la mostrarono tra una decina di cose: un razzo, un trattore,
all these technological things, and she’s there. [Laughing]
tutte queste cose tecnologiche, e lei è lì. [Ride]
Then there was Santoshi Ma,
Poi c'era Santoshi Ma,
who was a goddess created in Bollywood.
che era una dèa creata a Bollywood.
Then all these simple-hearted people went to see the movie,
Allora tutte queste persone semplici andarono a vedere il film,
and they showed this goddess, Santoshi Ma,
e mostrarono questa dèa, Santoshi Ma,
and here’s how you worship her,
e c'era anche come adorarla,
this is her mantra, this is her pūjā paraphenalia ...
questo è il suo mantra, questa l'attrezzatura per la sua pūjā...
All over India people started worshiping Santoshi Ma. [Laughing]
Ed in tutta l'India la gente cominciò ad adorare Santoshi Ma. [Ride]
Like the lady … Gurudev said, in Calcutta, one lady
Come la signora... Gurudev disse, a Calcutta, una signora
who was offering dandavats to so many stones,
che stava offrendo dandavat a parecchie pietre,
and they go, “Didi, what are you doing?”
e gli chiesero: «Didi che stai facendo?»
And she said, “One of them might be Śiva.”
e lei disse: «Una di loro potrebbe essere Shiva».
[Laughing]
[Ride]
So,
Allora,
when A.L. Basham came to the subject of māyāvād,
quando A.L. Basham affrontò l'argomento dei māyāvād,
the ultimate God-delusion that “I am God”—
la più alta illusione su Dio che "Io sono Dio"—
“I am God, you are God”,
sapete, "Io sono Dio, tu sei Dio"
or as John Lennon even mocked
oppure come perfino John Lennon diceva scherzando
in the beginning of “I am the Walrus”,
all'inizio di "I am the Walrus",
“I am he as you are he as you are me, And we are all together.”
"Io sono lui come tu sei lui come tu sei me e siamo tutti insieme".
So, on this subject A.L. Basham said,
Dunque, in merito a questo argomento A.L. Basham disse:
“I am you?” He said,
«Io sono te?».
[Laughing]
[Ride]
In one sentence he showed how silly that whole idea was.
In una frase mostrò quanto sciocca era quell'idea.